Charles Ruas Papers, 1924-2020: Finding Aid C1372
Manuscripts Division
Charles Ruas Papers
1974-1990
1860-2020
Manuscripts Division
Ruas, Charles
C1372
23 boxes
18.8 linear feet
9.8 GB
293 digital files
Charles Ruas is an American author, interviewer, editor, literary and art critic, and French translator, who served as the Director of the Drama and Literature Department for New York's Pacifica radio station WBAI-FM in the late 1970s and interviewed writers for radio broadcast and print, including Toni Morrison, Michel Foucault, Carlos Fuentes, Eudora Welty, Susan Sontag, Truman Capote, Buckminster Fuller, Andy Warhol, Mario Vargas Llosa, and others. Included are photographs and documents on Allen Ginsberg and William Burroughs, the St. Marks poetry project, and avant-garde artists and performers. The papers include transcripts and audiocassette tapes of Ruas's interviews with authors and artists, as well as typescripts and galleys of work by writers Ruas edited, including Marguerite Young, and some related photographs, notes, recordings, and correspondence. There are also some translations and other writings by Charles Ruas, as well as a collection of family photographs and papers documenting the history of his family in Tianjin, China, from the 1860s through the mid-20th century.
Appraisal
Nothing was removed from the collection during 2015-2021 processing beyond routine appraisal practices.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into five primary file groups: Author and Artist Files; Interviews, Radio, and Television; Photographs; Translations and Writings; and Family Papers and Tianjin History Collection.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Charles Ruas in 2014-2021 (AM 2014-100, AM 2014-106, AM 2014-107, AM 2015-4, AM 2016-44, AM 2017-56, AM 2019-4, 2019-97, 2020-39, 2020-68, and 2021-54).
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
This collection contains digital files, which may require specific software or hardware for access. Refer to our Tips on Accessing Born-Digital Content for information on how to render these file formats.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of materials related to Charles Ruas's work as a literary editor and interviewer, including transcripts, audiocassette tapes, and CD-ROMs of Ruas's interviews with writers and artists, typescripts and galleys of work by writers Ruas edited, manuscript materials he collected, as well as photographs, correspondence, recordings, and publicity materials that he kept regarding many of the authors with whom he worked.
Interview transcripts and recordings contain Ruas's author interviews, which he conducted for WBAI-FM, WPS1 Art Radio, The Paris Review, and Conversations with American Writers, a book of interviews he published in 1985. Writers represented in the interviews include Toni Morrison, Carlos Fuentes, Michel Foucault, Eudora Welty, Susan Sontag, Truman Capote, Buckminster Fuller, Andy Warhol, Mario Vargas Llosa, Norman Mailer, E. L. Doctorow, Tennessee Williams, Marguerite Young, James Laughlin, and others. While interviews primarily cover specific works by authors and the writing process, some tapes also document readings of work by writers and other live performances. The papers also include typescript drafts and galleys of books by writers whose work Ruas edited, including his own editorial drafts, as well as copies and manuscript materials that were gifted to him by authors, including Susan Howe, his co-host for poetry programming at WBAI-FM, and Marguerite Young, whose epic biography Harp Song for a Radical: The Life and Times of Eugene Victor Debs Ruas edited. Drafts and galleys of work by Helen Adam, Susan Sontag, and Djuna Barnes are also present, along with a group of dust jacket proofs. Also included are some correspondence, interview questions, photographs, and promotional materials from various writers Ruas interviewed or whose work he edited or reviewed.
A significant group of photographs of authors and artists was added to the collection beginning in 2016, including promotional photographs and portraits collected by Ruas, as well as shots from the WBAI recording studio. Some contact sheets and negatives are also present.
There are also some translations and other writings by Charles Ruas, including his translation of Death and the Labyrinth by Michel Foucault
A later addition includes a collection of family papers and photographs documenting the history of Tianjin, China, from the 1890s through the mid-20th century.
Related Materials
Selected first editions and inscribed books from Charles Ruas's library are held in the Rare Books Collection.
Audio files containing many of Charles Ruas's recorded interviews can be accessed on the website of Clocktower Productions in Conversations with Writers and Historic Audio from the Archives of Charles Ruas.
Ruas
Biographical / Historical
Charles Ruas is an American author, interviewer, editor, literary and art critic, and French translator. Born in Tientsin, China, in 1938, Ruas studied French, English, and Comparative Literature at Princeton University, where he received a BA in 1960, MA in 1963, and PhD in 1970. Ruas was a Fulbright scholar at the Sorbonne in 1963 and 1964. From 1974 to 1979, Ruas served as the Director of the Drama and Literature Department for New York's Pacifica station WBAI-FM, where he interviewed many famous cultural and literary icons and initiated several innovative literary programs, including the Audio-Experimental Theatre, which fostered collaboration among artists on multimedia projects for radio, and The Reading Experiment, a year-long series of readings from Marguerite Young's novel Miss MacIntosh, My Darling. Ruas also developed radio programming for the Museum of Modern Art's WPS1 Art Radio, served as an editor for Marguerite Young and other writers, published literary and art criticism for The Soho Weekly News, ARTnews, and Art in America, and conducted interviews of writers for The New York Times Book Review and The Paris Review. In 1985, Ruas published Conversations with American Writers, which includes a group of interviews from the early 1980s with several major writers, including Toni Morrison, Eudora Welty, Truman Capote, Susan Sontag, and others. He lives and works in New York City.
Authors and publishers -- New York (N.Y.) -- 20th century -- Interviews.; Authors, American -- 20th century -- Interviews.; Editors - New York (N.Y.) -- 20th century.; Experimental radio programs -- 20th century -- Sources.; Novelists, American -- 20th century -- Interviews.; Radio personalities -- 20th century -- Correspondence.; Shipbuilding -- China -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; China -- History -- Qing dynasty, 1644-1912 -- Sources; New York (N.Y.) -- Intellectual life -- 20th century.; Tianjin (China) -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Audiocassettes -- 20th century.; Interviews -- 20th century.; Photographs -- 20th century.; Proofs (printed matter) -- 20th century.; Transcripts -- 20th century.; WBAI Radio (New York, N.Y.); Howe, Susan, 1937-; Morrison, Toni; Nin, Anaïs.; Young, Marguerite, 1908-1995; Ruas family
- Author and Artist Files, 1960-2020; 9 boxes
  Arrangement
  Materials are arranged alphabetically by author name, followed by general groups dust jacket proofs, postcards, and catalogs.
  Scope and Contents
  Consists of typescript drafts, editorial copies, galleys, dust jacket proofs, and notes by other writers with whom Charles Ruas collaborated, including materials he received as gifts from authors, as well as materials directly related to books he edited. Writers represented include Marguerite Young, Susan Howe, Helen Adam, Djuna Barnes, and Susan Sontag. Most prominent are several works by American writer Marguerite Young, including materials regarding her epic biography Harp Song for a Radical: The Life and Times of Eugene Victor Debs. Ruas edited the unfinished manuscript after Young fell ill and could no longer continue writing the third part. The biography was posthumously published by Alfred A. Knopf in 1999. Several draft versions are present, including a copy of Young's 1742-page original draft, Ruas's working editorial draft, and his edited typescript of Part I with a group of unedited cut pages following it. A spiral notebook, containing Young's manuscript draft of a section of the book on Allan Pinkerton, along with some handwritten notes Young made on diner checks, are also included. In the last few years of her life, when she was very sick, Marguerite Young abandoned nonfiction and returned to writing poetry. Present here are Ruas's set of photocopied typescript and manuscript drafts of Young's last poems, most of which remain unpublished, Young's guide sheet for an unrealized dramatization of her earlier book Angel in the Forest, and a carbon copy of the original typescript of the first two chapters of Miss MacIntosh, My Darling, with handwritten corrections by Young, that the author inscribed and gifted to Ruas. Also of note is a typescript of an early book of collected poems by Susan Howe, Ruas's friend and poetry co-host at WBAI-FM. There are also several commercially available CDs of music and poetry recordings that Ruas collected.
  Also present are materials that Charles Ruas kept tucked inside of books given to him by writers he worked with as an interviewer, editor, and book reviewer. These materials include correspondence from writers and their publicists and assistants, Ruas's handwritten scripts and questions for interviews on WPS1 Art Radio, book publicity materials, and photographs of Anaïs Nin and William S. Burroughs taken at the WBAI-FM studio. While most correspondence is addressed to Ruas, some are letters addressed to his associates, Susan Howe and Rob Wynne. Most correspondence is brief and regards logistical details of author interviews and book reviews. Exceptions include a significant group of letters from Anaïs Nin to Rob Wynne, from the mid 1970s, and a strange, lengthy letter from writer Laura Riding Jackson to poet Susan Howe, regarding her distress over a potential interview. Individual letters from John Ashbery and Andy Warhol are also present. Materials removed from inscribed books are filed with photocopies of the inscribed pages. Selected first editions and inscribed books from Charles Ruas's library are held in the Rare Books Collection.
  While several photographs that were originally kept with related manuscripts and ephemera are present here, photographs of many of the authors and artists listed here can be found in the Photographs file group.
  - Adam, Helen, 1961-2008; 3 boxes
    - Adam, Helen, undated; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Consists of a San Francisco Burning typescript copy.
    - Adam, Helen, 1977-2008; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Primarily contains correspondence from Helen Adam, including tarot readings Adam did for Charles Ruas and Rob Wynne, and a photograph of her by Luke Wynne.
    - Adam, Helen, 1961-1977; 2 folders (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
      Immediate Source of Acquisition
      AM 2016-44
      Includes a typed script with performance notations for the stage version of the ballad opera San Francisco Burning performed at the Judson Church in New York City, along with a letter of rejection addressed to Helen Adam from the Public Theater. Also present is a portrait photograph of Helen Adam, circa 1977, taken by Luke Wynne.
  - Angelou, Maya, 1993; 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 1)
    AM 2020-68
    Copy of On the Pulse of Morning (Random House, NY), signed by Curt Asker.
  - Arensberg, Ann, 1990s; 2 boxes
    - Arensberg, Ann, 1991 June 29; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Arensberg, Ann, "Worm Life", undated; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 1)
      AM 2017-56
      Copy of typescript of novel titled "Worm Life," published by A. Knopf under the title Group Sex in 1986. 200 pages.
  - Asker, Curt, 1985-2019; 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 2)
    Catalog from 2019 Curt Asker retrospective in Stockholm with English translation prinout, as well as a photo poscard of Asker's "Le coeur du Luberon" (an installation), photo by his son, Jakob Asker, with a note written by his wife (1985).
  - Ashbery, John, 1985 August 7-30; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Atlas, Charles, 2011; 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 3)
    Catalog from "Dead Flowers," signed by Charles Atlas.
  - Ballard, J. G., 1990; 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 4)
    Copy of "The Atrocity Exhibition."
  - Barnes, Djuna, 1982; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Includes uncorrected galley proofs for Creatures in an Alphabet.
  - Bishop, Elizabeth, 2011; 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 5)
    Announcement for centenary.
  - Botsford, Gardner, 2005; 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 6)
    Memorial program.
  - Burroughs, William S., 1976; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 4)
    Portrait of Burroughs by Joan Schwartz and a letter from Burroughs's secretary, James Grauerholz, regarding taped interviews.
  - Campus, Peter, 1972-1977; 3 boxes
    - Campus, Peter, MoMA Video Art Exhibition Information Sheet, 1976-1977; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 2)
      MoMA information sheet for the first exhibition of video art by the museum curated by Barbara London. Additional notes on the show by Charles Ruas.
    - Campus, Peter, Art Performances Resume, 1977; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 1)
      AM 2017-110
    - Campus, Peter, Bykert Galley Show Card Announcement, 1972; 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Carr, Virginia Spencer, 1991; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Colwin, Laurie, 1972; 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 9)
    Photograph of Colwin by Nancy Crampton for memorial announcement with invitation.
  - Cooper, Wyatt, 1975-2013; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Dearborn, Mary V., 2004; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - The Expatriate Review, 1973-1974; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 3)
    Copy of Issue Number 4, Winter/Spring 1973-74.
  - Foucault, Michel, 1988 September 20; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 8)
    Includes a letter from Doubleday that accompanied Ruas's copies of Death and the Labyrinth.
  - Genet, Jean, circa 1964; 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 15)
    Vinyl record of "Jean Genet Directed by Howard Sackler" for Caedmon.
  - Giorno, John, 1973-2020; 1 box
    - Giorno, John, 2020; 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 10)
      Program for John Giorno memorial by Ugo Rondinone, his spouse.
    - Giorno, John, 1973; 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 11)
      Autograph copy of Cancer in My Left Ball.
  - Goldsmith, Barbara, circa 2005; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 9)
    Photocopy of inscription from book given to Charles Ruas.
  - Guggenheim, Peggy, 2004; 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 12)
    Invitation from NY Academy of Art including a photograph of Guggenheim on the roof terrace of Palazzo Venier dei Leoni, her home on the Grand Canal, Venice, Italy, 1950. Courtesy of Magnum Photos.
  - Harris, Julie, 1975; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Consists of a request to be a reader for Miss MacIntosh, My Darling and a note regretting that her schedule does not allow her to accept.
  - Henderson, Bill, 1979 December 27; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Heroes Are Gang Leaders, 2015-2016; 1 folder 2 CD-ROMs (Box 10, Folder 2)
    Two CDs titled "Flukum" and "Highest Engines Near/Near Higher Engineers."
  - Howe, Fanny, 1974; 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 13)
    Collection of notes and letters from Fanny Howe along with Charles Ruas's reply.
  - Howe, Susan, circa 1968-2019; 4 boxes
    - Howe, Susan, American Strand, circa 1968-1975; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 3)
      A typescript for a collection of early poetry.
    - Howe, Susan, Hinge Picture, 1974; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Chapbook.
    - Howe, Susan, Chanting at the Crystal Sea, 1975; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 3)
      Includes a Chanting at the Crystal Sea broadside, with cover design by David von Schlegell.
    - Howe, Susan, Notes on V.R. Lang and the Boston Poets Theatre, 1975-2014; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 5)
      Consists of Howe's notes for an introduction to V.R. Lang, and on the Boston Poets Theatre, co-founded by her mother, Mary Manning, which is the subject of a WBAI radio documentary by Howe.
    - Howe, Susan, Poetry Society of America Awards, 2017; 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 14)
      Program for 107th Annual Awards Ceremony at the Poetry Society of America.
  - Jackson, Laura Riding, 1976 February 5-1981 July 6; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 11)
    Includes a 1981 letter from Juris Jurjevics to Charles Ruas regarding a planned reissue of Laura Riding Jackson's Progress of Stories, as well as a 1976 letter from Laura Riding Jackson to poet and WBAI collaborator Susan Howe regarding taped interviews.
  - Jonas, Joan, 1976-2015; 3 boxes
    - Jonas, Joan, 2007; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Jonas, Joan, 2015; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 6)
      Copy of script for the voiceover for the video projection in "They Come to Us Without a Word," the Venice Biennale 2015.
    - Jonas, Joan, 1976-2010; 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 1)
      Postcard from Nova Scotia (1976) and show announcements with Joan Jonas photograph taken by Ragani Haas, Queens Museum (2003); Fabric Workshop Museum (2010); and Joan Jonas driving with Sappho to Nova Scotia taken by Brigitte Cornand, Anthology Film Archives (2006).
  - Jurjevics, Juris, 2019; undated; 2 boxes
    - Jurjevics, Juris, undated; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 13)
      Contains Ruas's script and questions for an interview with Jurjevics for WPS1.
    - Jurjevics, Juris, 2019; 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - King, Dave, 2005; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 14)
    Includes Ruas's script and questions for an interview with King for WPS1.
  - Kosiński, Jerzy, 1975-1993; 2 boxes
    - Kosiński, Jerzy, 1976-1982; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Kosiński, Jerzy, 1975-1993; 4 folders (Box 6, Folder 4-7)
      Includes contact sheets, photographs, and negatives of Jerzy Kosiński with Charles Ruas at Radio Station WBAI Pacifica in New York City taken by Joan Schwartz, circa 1975, as well as several publicity photographs taken by Kathyrn M. Tidyman. Also a 1993 letter from Jaromir Jedliński to Charles Ruas regarding Kosiński, a printout of Henry Dasko's study "Kosiński's Afterlife," and a Muzeum Sztuki w Łodzi catalog dedicated to Kosiński.
  - Lalanne, François-Xavier, and Claude, 1991-2019; 2 boxes
    - Lalanne, François-Xavier, and Claude, 1991; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 7)
      2 copies of illustrated and handwritten menus for the dinner celebrating the Les Lalannes exhibition at the Château de Chenonceau installed by Peter Marino.
    - Lalanne, François-Xavier, and Claude, 2005-2019; 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 3)
      Show announcement for Claude and François-Xavier Lalanne, JGM (Galerie 2005), taken in their garden at Ury, France, and a funeral announcement for Madame Claude Lelanne (April 10, 2019, Ury).
  - Leffingwell, Edward, 2009; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 8)
    Consists of a completed chapter from Leffingwell's proposal for an unpublished biography of Jack Smith. This chapter is an account of the underground film community of New York, in which Jack Smith and Andy Warhol were major figures, containing biographical information and details about his work by a participant who later curated Jack Smith's first retrospective at P.S.1. 75 pages.
  - Listfield, Emily, 1994; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Llosa, Mario Vargas, 1984 May 16; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 17)
    Contains a letter from Helene Atwan at Farrar, Straus & Giroux, regarding Llosa, that was originally kept in Ruas's proof copy of Aunt Julia and the Scriptwriter.
  - McEvilley, Thomas, 1982; 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 4)
    44 Four Line Poems, Full Court Press, Los Angeles.
  - McIntyre, Vestal, undated; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 18)
    Includes Ruas's script and questions for an interview with McIntyre for WPS1.
  - Michel, Prince of Greece, 2011 June; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 19)
    Includes a note, addressed to Rob Wynne, regarding a gifted breviary from the Royal Chapel at Versailles.
  - Nathan, Jean, 2004; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - "Niki de Saint-Phalle", 2014; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 9)
    Program for exhibition at Grand Palais, Galeries Nationales.
  - Nin, Anaïs, 1974-1975; 2 boxes
    - Nin, Anaïs, 1974-1976; 2 folders (Box 5, Folder 21-22)
      Includes correspondence between Nin and Rob Wynne, along with a draft of Nin's preface for a new edition of Marguerite Young's Miss MacIntosh, My Darling.
    - Nin, Anaïs, "Under the Sign of Pisces", 1974 Fall; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 10)
      Copy of "Under the Sign of Pisces" and newsletter announcing the WBAI programs on Marguerite Young.
  - O'Hara, Frank, 2003; 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 5)
    Announcement for celebration at the Poetry Society of America with drawing of O'Hara by Nell Blaine, 1952.
  - Padgett, Ron, 2004; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Post, Steve, 2014 August 3; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 11)
    "Playing the FM Band" memorial program.
  - Quinlan, Alexis, undated; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Quinn, Alice, 2006-2008; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Sanders, Ed, 1977 August 31; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Seldes, Marian, 1975; 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 6)
    Postcards on reading Marguerite Young.
  - Sikelianos, Eleni, 2004; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Simon, Paul, and Alice Quinn, 2019; 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 7)
    Publication by the Poetry Society of America honoring Simon and Quinn.
  - Sontag, Susan, 1982-1984; 1 box
    - Conversations with American Writers, Susan Sontag Chapter Galleys, 1984; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Susan Sontag Reader, Galleys, 1982; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Spanidou, Irini, 1986 March 3-April 18; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Von Schlegell, David, 1965; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 8)
    Includes an exhibition announcement for a 1965 show at Royal Marks Gallery featuring a photograph of Susan Howe.
  - Waldman, Anne, 2017; 1 folder 1 CD-ROM (Box 10, Folder 3)
    One CD titled "Untethered."
  - Waldman, Brahja, 2013-2016; 1 folder 3 CD-ROMs (Box 10, Folder 4)
    Three CDs titled "wisdomatic" and "Cosmic Brahjas" / "Closer to the Tones."
  - Warhol, Andy, 1980 February 27; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Welty, Eudora, 1990; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 9)
    Includes an exhibition announcement for a show of photographs by Eudora Welty at the Old Capital Museum, inscribed by her to artist Rob Wynne.
  - Willis, Susan, 2005; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 30)
    Includes Ruas's script and questions for an interview with Willis for WPS1.
  - Woodman, Francesca, 2015; 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 8)
    Postcard.
  - Young, Marguerite, circa 1960-1999; 5 boxes
    - Young, Marguerite, Angel in the Forest, Guide Sheet for Dramatization, undated; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Prepared for director Tom O'Horgon and actor Victor Limpari's script for a dramatization of Angel in the Forest. The project was never completed.
    - Young, Marguerite, Harp Song for a Radical, Notes, undated; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Includes Young's handwritten notes on checks from Riker's, a luncheonette in the West Village where Young often worked on her biography of Eugene V. Debs, along with a typescript list of names related to the book.
    - Young, Marguerite, Harp Song for a Radical, Manuscript Draft of Section on Allan Pinkerton, undated; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Manuscript draft in spiral notebook.
    - Young, Marguerite, Harp Song for a Radical, Original Draft with Edits, 1994-1999; 11 folders (Box 1, Folder 10-20)
      Photocopy of original typescript, as it was submitted to Victoria Wilson, Young's editor at Knopf, who asked Charles Ruas to edit the manuscript for publication. Wilson's assistant, Lee Buttala, gave Ruas this copy, following the book's publication in 1999. A note from Buttala and a book publisher's catalog are also included.
    - Young, Marguerite, Harp Song for a Radical, Working Editorial Draft, circa 1994-1999; 8 folders (Box 2, Folder 1-8)
      Copy of edited typescript.